Guide to the New York Caledonian Club Records 1856-2007 MS 2923
New-York Historical Society
New York Caledonian Club records
1856-2007
New-York Historical Society
New York Caledonian Club
MS 2923
7.5 Linear feet 38 bound volumes, 4 boxes (3 oversize folders)
The Records of the New York Caledonian Club document the work, activities, and membership of this society dedicated to the preservation of Scottish heritage, from its founding in 1856 through 2007. The collection contains administrative records, award citations, monographs, newsletters, photographs, Scottish Studies Program documents, scrapbooks, and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection consists of three donations:
1. The photograph collection was a Gift of the New York Caledonian Club in 1934.
2. Two volumes received at an unknown date.
3. The membership registers, minutes, and related documents were a Gift of the New York Caledonian Club in 2012.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in twelve series. The arrangement within each series is chronological.
Series I: Minutes, 1856 - 2003
Series II. Photographs, 1857 - 1918
Series III: Membership Records, 1856 - 1947
Series IV: Financial Records, 1919 - 1994
Series V: Charter, By-Laws, and Rules and Regulations, 1861 - 2002
Series VI: Award Citations and Proclamations, 1982 - 2007
Series VII: Library Records, 1888 - 1942
Series VIII: Newsletters, 1985 - 1990
Series IX: Scottish Studies Program, 2000 - 2002
Series X: Monographs
Series XI: Ephemera
Series XII: Flag
Biographical / Historical
The New York Caledonian Club was founded in 1856 to provide a social community for Scottish immigrants and their descendents and to support the preservation of Scottish history, language, and culture. The club's activities were as varied as its membership. Laborers and skilled tradesmen gathered with wealthy individuals to promote Scottish heritage through literary evenings, athletic events, traditional Scottish celebrations, education, and philanthropy.
The club's direct antecedent was an early Caledonian Club founded in 1830 by members of the Highland Guard after the war of 1812. In 1857, the New York Caledonian Club inaugurated the annual "Highland Games" (also known as the "Scotch Games").The games were a major amateur athletic competition in traditional Scottish sporting events, such as curling and hammer throwing. The games took place in Jones Wood, a stretch of farmland along the East River that predated urban Manhattan's Upper East Side.
The New York Caledonian Club was officially chartered and incorporated in the City of New York in 1861. The club's purpose, as expressed in its founding charter, included establishing a library. Club member and philanthropist Andrew Carnegie donated three thousand volumes. (The library was later given to the Second Presbyterian Church, where many New York Caledonian Club members worshipped.)
In 1861, the club formed the 79th New York Highland Regiment in response to President Abraham Lincoln's urgent appeal for volunteers for the Union Army. The "Seventy-Ninth" was the only kilted Civil War regiment. The Regiment fought in numerous battles, including the first battle of Bull Run, served under General Ulysses S. Grant at Vicksburg, and assisted Admiral Dupont in capturing Port Royal.
In 1873, the club formed a committee to erect a statue of the legendary Scottish poet Robert Burns on Central Park's "literary walk." A Scottish sculptor, Mr. John Steell, R.S.A., was commissioned to create the artwork, which was officially unveiled on October 1, 1880.
The New York Caledonian Club became inactive after World War II. It was revived on June 24, 1981 on Bannockburn Night, which commemorates the 1314 battle in which Robert the Bruce led the Scots to victory over the English forces. On July 1, 1982, the New York Caledonian Club won recognition for Scottish culture with the official proclamation of "Tartan Day" by New York Governor Hugh Carey and New York City Mayor Edward Koch. Tartan Day commemorated the 200th anniversary of the repeal of the 1747 Act of Proscription, a law that forbade Scots to wear the tartan, the national Scottish highland dress.
The New York Caledonian Club continues to promote the study of Scottish literature and practice of cultural traditions. Their signature event is the annual Robert Burns supper. The club's Scottish Studies Program focuses on the writings of Robert Burns, as well as Scottish Gaelic language studies, musical instruction in playing the bagpipes, and Highland dancing.
Related Materials
Additional materials related to the New York Caledonian Club can be located by searching the library's online catalog. These include "The Caledonian," a monthly magazine published by the club from 1901-1923, pamphlets, event programs and other materials.
Other items pertaining to the New York Caledonian Club may be located by searching the museum's online catalog.
Scope and Contents
The New York Caledonian Club Records (1856 - 2007) document the membership, internal meetings, administrative and financial functions, social events, Scottish Studies Program, public issuances of the organization, and circulation of the club's lending library. The bulk of the collection consists of handwritten minutes from 1856-2003. Documents, such as the New York Caledonian Club's Constitution, are glued onto pages in early bound volumes of minutes. Minutes from 1981-2002 were typewritten and interfiled chronologically by the club secretary with correspondence, financial records, and public issuances. Membership books (1856-1947) record names and the diverse occupations of club members, as well as their birthplaces, birth dates, death dates, and years of membership. The club's library function is documented in the lending library logbook. The collection includes the New York Caledonian Club flag, flown during the Highland Games (Scotch Games).
The general highlights of this collection are the photographs (1859-1918) and the register of the 79th New York Highland Regiment (volume 20). Twenty-two silver gelatin and albumen photographs (many are oversized) include portraits of club officers in Highland dress, veterans of the kilted Civil War regiment, and photographs of the Scotch Games. The register of the 79th Regiment includes two notable letters. A Special Order dated June 28, 1865, names New York Caledonian Club Chief George Mitchell (1832-1884) as Quartermaster of the 79th Regiment. The order is signed by Lieutenant Colonel Samuel M. Elliott (1811-1875), a Caledonian Club member who was later promoted to Brigadier General by President Abraham Lincoln. An October 31, 1881 letter by U.S. Secretary of State James Blaine expresses gratitude to the club for their condolences upon the assassination of President James Garfield.
Albumen prints.; Correspondence.; Gelatin silver prints.; Photographic prints.; Posters.; Registers (lists); Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Parades -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Scottish Americans -- Clothing -- Photographs.; Scottish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Societies, etc.; Veterans -- New York (State); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Participation, Scottish.; Fraser, Alexander, 1819-1914; Fyfe, Thomas Alexander, 1853-1928; Reid, William; New York Caledonian Club; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 79th (1859-1876)
- Series I: Minutes, 1856-2003
  Scope and Contents
  Bound ledgers of handwritten minutes run from the New York Caledonian Club's founding in 1856 through 1950 and are arranged chronologically. Folders of typewritten minutes run from 1981 through 2002. There are no minutes from 1950-1982. The majority of the bound ledgers include minutes of Board of Trustees meetings as well as annual meetings, monthly meetings, and meetings of subcommittees. They include discussion of club business, from election of officers, to acceptance of members, adjudication of disputes between members, planning of annual events such as the Robert Burns dinner and Highland Games, as well as exceptional campaigns, such as financial aid to members and non-members during wars. Many volumes have key documents glued in to the ledgers. The New York Caledonian Club Constitution is glued to pages in volume 12. Other documents pertaining to the time-period encompassed in the ledger have been placed inside the back covers of ledgers. Typewritten minutes from 1981-2002 were kept together chronologically by the club secretary with flyers, program brochures, newsletters, clippings, and ephemera pertaining to the same time period.
  - Minutes, 1867 January 18 - 1870 December 3 (Offsite-box CA-2, Volume 1)
  - Minutes, 1868 January 14 - 1881 March 29 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 2)
  - Minutes, 1871 January 3 - 1873 December 9 (Offsite-box CA-2, Volume 3)
  - Minutes, 1874 January 6 - 1881 March 1 (Offsite-box CA-3, Volume 4)
  - Mintues, 1881 April 3 - 1887 December 27 (Offsite-box CA-3, Volume 5)
  - Mintues, 1888 January 3 - 1892 May 9 (Offsite-box CA-3, Volume 6)
  - Mintues, 1891 January 27 - 1897 December 28 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 7)
  - Minutes, 1892 June 7 - 1899 August 1 (Offsite-box CA-2, Volume 8)
  - Minutes, 1897 January 12 - 1900 September 27 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 9)
  - Minutes, 1898 February 23 - 1902 December 30 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 10)
  - Minutes, 1899 September 5 - 1909 September 6 (Offsite-box CA-1, Volume 11)
  - Minutes, 1903 January 27 - 1908 December 2 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 12)
  - Minutes, 1909 May 4 - 1918 July 2 (Offsite-box CA-1, Volume 13)
  - Minutes, 1918 August 6 - 1927 June 30 (Offsite-box CA-1, Volume 14)
  - Minutes, 1927 July 5 - 1937 May 4 (Offsite-box CA-6, Volume 15)
  - Minutes, 1933 June 19 - 1944 February (Offsite-box CA-7, Volume 16)
  - Minutes, 1937 September 7 - 1950 February 3 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 17)
  - Minutes, 1981 November 4 - 1982 June 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1982 July 1 - 1982 October 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1987 September 16 - 1989 November 16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1990 January 10 - 1991 October 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1991 January 7 - 1991 December 24 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1992 March 10 - 1992 July 31 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1992 August 28 - 1993 January 5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1995 January 17 - 1995 June 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1994 January 12 - 1994 November 29 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 2000 May 7 - 2000 December 18 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 2001 January 22 - 2001 June 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 2001 July 9 - 2001 September 10 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 2001 October 15 - 2001 December 11 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2002 January 7 - 2002 May 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Photographs, 1857-1918
  This series consists of 22 silver gelatin and albumen photographs of New York Caledonian Club members in Highland dress. One hand-tinted photograph (1866) features a club officer bearing the Caledonian Club's gold flag, which was flown at Highland Games. Most photographs are larger than 14 x 18 inches.
  - Portraits, 1866 - 1904 (Box OS Medium, Folder New York Caledonian Club Records)
    There are seven oversize studio photographs (1866 - 1904) of New York Caledonian Club officers in individual and small group portraits. These include: William Clelland (1866); Alex Fraser (1857); Thomas Fyffe (1870); William G. Reid (1904); William Inglis, Thomas Barclay, and William Cunningham (undated); John Taylor, James West, John Young, William Manson, and Geo. Mitchell, Jr. (1880) C. Sanderson, D. Miller, W. Thomson, R. Cockburn, and K. Mackenzie (undated); and five unnamed officers (undated).
  - Caledonian Club Building (Box OS Medium, Folder New york Caledonian Club Records)
    This is a photograph of the exterior of the New York Caledonian Club's marble mansion, located at 846 Seventh Avenue (54th Street). The club acquired the building in 1898.
  - Scotch Games and Parades, 1859 - 1915 (Box OS Medium, Folder New York Caledonian Club Records)
    Four oversize photographs show large assemblies of club members at the annual Scotch Games, held at Jones Wood in New York City.
  - 79th New York Highland Regiment, 1861-1918 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    This folder contains a group portrait of Robert Gair, Lawrence Beattie, and George Arnott in 1861, just before the 79th Regiment departed to defend the Washington, D.C. The photograph is mounted with reproductions of the 79th Regiment Medal from the Battle of Bull Run. There is also a photograph of the 50th Anniversary (1911) parade of Regiment veterans en route to the Second Presbyterian Church. There is a photograph of the dedication of a monument to the 79th Regiment at Knoxville, Tennesee on September 28, 1918. Regiment veterans in the monument dedication photograph include Andrew D. Baird, Robert Gair, Robert Armour, Joseph Stewart, Frank M. Chamberlin, Henry Bloomfield, and John Muir.
  - Scotch Games and Parades, 1859 - 1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    This folder contains two mounted photographs of the Scotch Games (1904 and 1914) and a mounted photograph of the Caledonian Club in the 1910 New York City Labor Day parade.
- Series III: Membership Records, 1856-1947
  The Membership Records, 1856-1947 are composed of seven bound volumes running from the New York Caledonian Club's founding in 1856 through 1947. Some volumes are organized alphabetically by indexed letter tabs. Others list rosters of members by calendar year. The volumes contain columned pages with entries for each individual member's name, address, profession, club admission date, club membership expiration date (if relevant), and notes.
  Volume 20, the registry of members of the 79th New York Highland Regiment, founded by the New York Caledonian Club in 1861 in response to President Lincoln's call for Union Army volunteers, is of particular interest. Two loose letters are encased in the volume. The Regiment's Quartermaster, George Mitchell, is appointed in a Special Order dated June 28, 1865. The order is signed by Lieutenant Colonel Samuel M. Elliott (1811-1875), a Caledonian Club member who was later promoted to Brigadier General by President Abraham Lincoln. An October 31, 1881 letter by U.S. Secretary of State James Blaine expresses gratitude to the club for condolences expressed upon the assassination of President James Garfield.
  - Membership Records, 1856 November 14 - 1934 December 1 (Offsite-box CA-6, Volume 18)
  - Membership Records, 1860-1940 November 12 (Offsite-box CA-2, Volume 19)
  - Registry, 79th Regiment, 1865 - 1917 (Offsite-box CA-5, Volume 20)
  - Membership Records, 1900 - 1910 (Offsite-box CA-5, Volume 21)
  - Membership Records, 1917 - 1919 (Offsite-box CA-5, Volume 22)
  - Membership Records, 1935 - 1928 (Offsite-box CA-4, Volume 23)
  - Membership Records, 1928 - 1947 (Offsite-box CA-7, Volume 24)
- Series IV: Financial Records, 1919-1994
  Bound ledgers, receipt books, and one spiral notebook record monthly receipts and disbursements for club activities and membership dues.
  - Property Committee Journal, 1919 January - December 1938 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 27)
  - Ledger, 1919 January - 1923 December (Offsite-box CA-3, Volume 28)
  - Receipt Book, 1926 January - 1926 October (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 29)
  - Receipt Book, 1931 October 14 - 1939 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 30)
  - Ledger, 1931 - 1934 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 31)
  - Receipt Book, 1944 October 14 - 1950 March 4 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 32)
  - Financial Notebooks, 1992 April 26 - 1994 March 25 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- Series V: Charter, By-Laws, and Rules and Regulations, 1861 - 2002
  This series includes the New York Caledonian Club's February 5, 1861 founding charter as well as the Club Rules and Regulations (1911) and By-Laws (2002).
  - Founding Charter and Certificate of Incorporation, 1861 January 5 (Box OS Medium)
  - By-Laws and Rules and Regulations, 1911 - 2002 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Award Citations and Proclamations, 1982-2007
  This folder of oversize material includes the proclamations by New York State Governor Hugh Carey and New York City Mayor Edward Koch commemorating National Tartan Day, July 1, 1982.
  - Award Citations and Proclamations, 1982 - 2007 (Box OS Medium)
- Series VII: Library Records, 1888-1942
  The Library Records, 1888 - 1942 are composed of two bound volumes. Volume 25 records the club member's name, the title of the book loaned from the New York Caledonian Club library, the book's shelf number, the date the book was borrowed, and the date the book was returned. Page one of Volume 25 states: "The above copied over from previous book." There is no prior library logbook in this collection, however. Volume 26 is blank.
  - Library Logbook, 1888 - 1942 (Offsite-box CA-5, Volume 25)
  - Library Logbook (Offsite-box CA-9, Volume 26)
    Volume 26 is blank.
- Series VIII: Newsletters, 1985-1990
  This folder contains the New York Caledonian Club's newsletter from November 1985 - January 1990, including editorial notes and correspondence pertaining to production of the publication.
  - Newsletters, 1985 November 1 - 1990 January (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- Series: IX: Scottish Studies Program, 2000-2002
  - Scottish Studies Program, 2000 - 2002 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    This folder includes the May 6, 2002 Scottish Studies Committee Report, draft and final publications of the Program of Scottish Studies and e-mail correspondence about enrollment, rates, and course content.
- Series X: Monographs, 1848, 1925 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 35)
  - Cramm, Richard (undated). The First Five Hundred. Albany: C.F. Williams & Son, Inc. (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 35)
  - MacBean, William M. (1925). Biographical Register of Saint Andrew's Society of the State of New York. Printed for the Society. (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 36)
  - McIan, R.R. (1848). Gaellic Gatherings; or, The Highlanders at Home, on the Heath, the River, and the Loch--A Series of Highly Interesting Plates Representing Picturesque Groups Engaged in their Social Employments, their Sports, and Pastimes. (Offsite-box CA-7, Volume 37)
- Series XI: Ephemera, 1928-2001
  This series includes an oversize 1898 poster for the New York Caledonian Club's 41st annual excursion to Oriental Grove. Volume 33 is a scrapbook of the club's 70th Anniverssary Dinner-Dance (November 27, 1926). Volume 34 is a scrapbook of invitations to monthly and annual meetings (1928 - 1935). A folder of ephemera (January 25, 1992 - January 27, 2001) includes event programs, flyers, application forms, club brochures, and an undated statistical survey of club members.
  - Poster, 1898 (Box OS Medium)
  - Scrapbook, 1928 December 31 - 1935 February 26 (Offsite-box CA-9, Volume 33)
  - Scrapbook, 1926 November 27 (Offsite-box CA-8, Volume 34)
  - Blank Scrapbook (Offsite-box CA-7, Volume 38)
  - Ephemera, 1992 January 25 - 2001 January 27 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- Series XII: Flag, 1988
  This flag was made in 1988. It is a replica of the New York Caledonian Club flag flown during the annual Highland Games (Scotch Games) in Jones Woods.
  - New York Caledonian Club Flag (Offsite-box 4)